Evil fears the knight.
Batman Begins is a drama, crime, action film directed by Christopher Nolan.
Driven by tragedy, billionaire Bruce Wayne dedicates his life to uncovering and
defeating the corruption that plagues his home, Gotham City.
Unable to work within the system, he instead creates a new identity, a
symbol of fear for the criminal underworld - The Batman.
Bruce Wayne / Batman, played by Christian Bale.
Alfred, played by Michael Caine.
Ducard, played by Liam Neeson.
Rachel Dawes, played by Katie Holmes.
Jim Gordon, played by Gary Oldman.
Dr. Jonathan Crane, played by Cillian Murphy.
Batman Begins is a 2005 superhero film based on the DC Comics character Batman.
Directed by Christopher Nolan, who co-wrote the screenplay with David S.
Goyer, the film stars Christian Bale as Bruce Wayne / Batman, with Michael Caine, Liam Neeson, Katie Holmes, Gary
Oldman, Cillian Murphy, Tom Wilkinson, Rutger Hauer, Ken Watanabe, and Morgan Freeman in supporting roles.
The film reboots the Batman film series, telling the origin story of Bruce Wayne from the death of his parents to his journey to
become Batman and his fight to stop Ra's al Ghul (Neeson) and the Scarecrow (Murphy) from plunging Gotham City into chaos.
After Batman & Robin (1997) was panned by critics and
underperformed at the box office, Warner Bros.
Pictures cancelled future Batman films, including Joel
Schumacher's planned Batman Unchained.
Between 1998 and 2003, several filmmakers collaborated with Warner Bros.
in attempting to reboot the franchise.
After the studio rejected a Batman origin story reboot Joss
Whedon pitched in December 2002, Warner Bros.
hired Nolan in January 2003 to direct a new film.
Nolan and Goyer began development on the film in early 2003.
Aiming for a darker, more realistic tone compared to the previous films, a primary goal for their vision was to engage
the audience's emotional investment in both the Batman and Bruce Wayne identities of the lead character.
The film, which was principally shot in the United Kingdom, Iceland and Chicago, relied heavily on traditional stunts and
miniature effects, with computer-generated imagery being used in a minimal capacity compared to other action films.
Comic book storylines such as The Man Who Falls, Batman: Year One,
and Batman: The Long Halloween served as inspiration.
Expectations for Batman Begins ranged from moderate to low, which originated from the poor reception
of Batman & Robin that was credited with stalling the Batman film series in 1997.
After premiering in Tokyo on May 31, 2005, the film was
released in the United States on June 15.
It was a critical and commercial success, grossing over $371.9 million worldwide against a $150 million budget, becoming the ninth
highest-grossing film of 2005, and was the second highest grossing Batman film at the time of its release, behind Tim Burton's Batman (1989).
Receiving a nomination for the Academy Award for Best Cinematography, the film elevated
Bale to leading man status while it made Nolan a high-profile director.
Since its release, Batman Begins has often been cited as one
of the most influential films of the 2000s.
The film helped popularize the term reboot in Hollywood, inspiring studios and
filmmakers to revive franchises with realistic and serious tones.
It was followed by The Dark Knight (2008) and The Dark Knight Rises (2012),
with the three films constituting The Dark Knight trilogy.
The film explores themes of martial arts, undercover, loss of
loved one, secret identity, crime fighter.
The tone is emotional.